<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.flowable.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.flowable.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-21T16:01:11+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/</id><title>Flowable</title><subtitle>The BPMN engine</subtitle><entry><title>Flowable 6.1.1 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/07/21/flowable-6.1.1-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 6.1.1 release" /><published>2017-07-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/07/21/flowable-6.1.1-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/07/21/flowable-6.1.1-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released a new version of Flowable with the 6.1.1 release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6.1.1 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of audit history in the DMN Engine. When history is enabled in the DMN Engine, an audit log of each decision execution is stored in the DMN database. By default the history is disabled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replaced the MVEL expression language in the DMN Engine with the same JUEL expression language as used in the BPMN and Form Engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refactored DmnRuleService with new ExecuteDecisionBuilder and deprecated old execute decision methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call activity: allow to set output parameters a local variables for multi instance executions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier usage of async history in combination with a message queue (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-examples/tree/master/async-history&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-examples/tree/master/async-history&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance improvement: introduce grouping and compression for async history data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various small bugfixes all around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community contributors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faizal Abdul Manan (faizal-manan)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Malkovsky (dbmalkovsky)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harsha Teja Kanna (h7kanna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lori Small (lsmall)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bsydow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stephraleigh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgrade notes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;CommandContext and related classes package changes:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of a refactoring that involved consolidating various classes and moving them to the &lt;i&gt;flowable-engine-common&lt;/i&gt; module, following &lt;i&gt;internal&lt;/i&gt; classes have changed packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following applies to all engines (process, dmn, form, content and idm):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;i&gt;CommandContext&lt;/i&gt; class is now in the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.common.impl.interceptor&lt;/i&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The various getter methods on the &lt;i&gt;CommandContext&lt;/i&gt; that gave quick-access to various internal components are removed 
(because the CommandContext is now shared between all engines). All engines now have a &lt;i&gt;CommandContextUtil&lt;/i&gt; class that 
should be used instead and which has said getter methods. The &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.impl.context.Context&lt;/i&gt; utlity class 
in the process engine is still there for backwards compatibility and can be used as before, but simply delegates to the &lt;i&gt;CommandContextUtil&lt;/i&gt; methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The classes related to the command stack interceptors (&lt;i&gt;Command&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;CommandContextInterceptor&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;CommandExecutor&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Log/Jta/RetryInterceptor&lt;/i&gt;) are now in the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.common.impl.interceptor&lt;/i&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;i&gt;DbSqlSession&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;DbSqlSessionFactory&lt;/i&gt; classes are now found in the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.common.impl.db&lt;/i&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Database schema management logic has moved from the &lt;i&gt;DbSqlSession&lt;/i&gt; class to implementations of the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.common.impl.db.DbSchemaManager&lt;/i&gt; interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;i&gt;GenericManagerFactory&lt;/i&gt; class is now in the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.common.impl.persistence&lt;/i&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process engine now has the &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.impl.util.EngineServiceUtil&lt;/i&gt; utility class that can be used to get easily access to the configuration and services of the other engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;FlowableCancelledEvent.getCause() return value change&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value that&amp;#39;s passed in the &lt;i&gt;cause&lt;/i&gt; of a &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.engine.delegate.event.FlowableCancelledEvent&lt;/i&gt; has changed in the following cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The event that is thrown for activities cancelled by a &lt;i&gt;message boundary event&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The event that is thrown for activities cancelled by a &lt;i&gt;signal boundary event&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The event that is thrown for activities cancelled by a &lt;i&gt;timer boundary event&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of passing an entity instance (MessageEventSubscriptionEntity, SignalEventSubscriptionEntity or JobEntity respectively) the BpmnModel
counterpart, as an instance of a subclass of &lt;i&gt;org.flowable.bpmn.model.FlowElement&lt;/i&gt;, is passed instead which is consistent with the general value of the &lt;i&gt;cause&lt;/i&gt; property.
Do note that due to the fact the return type of &lt;i&gt;getCause()&lt;/i&gt; is &lt;i&gt;Object&lt;/i&gt;, the compiler will not notice this, so best to look at the usage of the &lt;i&gt;FlowableCancelledEvent&lt;/i&gt; in your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible.
You can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions about the 6.1.1 release, any feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released a new version of Flowable with the 6.1.1 release.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 6.1.0 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/06/27/flowable-6.1.0-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 6.1.0 release" /><published>2017-06-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/06/27/flowable-6.1.0-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/06/27/flowable-6.1.0-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released a new version of Flowable with the 6.1.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6.1.0 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of async history. By enabling the asyncHistoryEnabled property on the process engine configuration (default is false), the history tables are not filled in the same transaction as the runtime tables. Instead an async history job is created and the history information will be written to the history tables in a separate, asynchronous transaction. This also opens up the option to not use the relational history tables at all, and move the historic information to a NoSQL database directly. Pluggability points are available to implement the persistence logic to a NoSQL database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New REST task feature thanks to Harsha. With the new REST task it becomes trivial to do REST calls from a Flowable process instance. There&amp;#39;s also support in the Flowable Modeler for REST tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of a new DMN decision table editor. To improve the usability of the DMN decision table editor we are now using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/handsontable/handsontable&quot;&gt;Handsontable&lt;/a&gt; framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Odysseus JUEL code is now included directly in the flowable-engine-common module to prevent classloading issues due to conflicting JUEL libraries or even different versions of JUEL libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added option to use a password encoder for the Flowable IDM engine (instead of the default plain text password persistence), thanks to Faizal!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for static Groovy scripts compilation with the new flowable-groovy-script-static-engine module by using the groovy-static scriptFormat value, thanks to Filip (fgroch)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several additions to the Form builder and renderer (min/max length, improved expression field and more).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various small bugfixes all around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible.
You can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions about the 6.1.0 release, any feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released a new version of Flowable with the 6.1.0 release.</summary></entry><entry><title>Welcome back Joram Barrez</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/05/29/welcome-back-joram.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome back Joram Barrez" /><published>2017-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/05/29/welcome-back-joram</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/05/29/welcome-back-joram.html">&lt;p&gt;Joram Barrez has been one of the driving forces for open source BPM for almost 10 years. 
So it wasn&amp;#39;t easy when he needed to step away for some time from the Flowable project.
But now he&amp;#39;s back and fully committed to help driving the Flowable project with lots of new energy and ideas.
From the whole Flowable team and community, we just wanted to say: &amp;quot;Welcome back Joram!&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also taking this opportunity to add a link to our new Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/wiki/Flowable-roadmap&quot;&gt;roadmap page&lt;/a&gt;.
If you want to see other features being added to the roadmap, get in contact with us on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;Flowable forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Joram Barrez has been one of the driving forces for open source BPM for almost 10 years. 
So it wasn&amp;#39;t easy when he needed to step away for some time from the Flowable project.
But now he&amp;#39;s back and fully committed to help driving the Flowable project with lots of new energy and ideas.
From the whole Flowable team and community, we just wanted to say: &amp;quot;Welcome back Joram!&amp;quot;.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 6.0.1 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/28/flowable-6.0.1-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 6.0.1 release" /><published>2017-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/28/flowable-6.0.1-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/28/flowable-6.0.1-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released the first bug fix version of the Flowable 6 engine (6.0.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6.0.1 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First bug fix release for Flowable 6!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved LDAP support for the UI apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The i18n in the UI apps is now pluggable and there are some first additional languages included&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved event sub process support with nested event sub process support for non interrupting ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More hit policy support in the DMN Engine. The Decision Table editor will be updated in the Flowable 6.1.0 release. The DMN Engine API has been refactored to take into account single and multiple output result objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various small bugfixes all around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible.
You can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions about the 6.0.1 release, any feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released the first bug fix version of the Flowable 6 engine (6.0.1).</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable Enterprise Support Now Available</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/04/enterprise-support.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable Enterprise Support Now Available" /><published>2017-04-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/04/enterprise-support</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/04/04/enterprise-support.html">&lt;p&gt;You may have already seen that core developers from the Flowable Project have joined forces with edorasware. 
This doesn’t change our commitment to open source, if anything, it gives us an opportunity to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it does mean is that there is now Enterprise Support available for the open source Flowable engines, backed by the people that architected and wrote them. 
You can get a support subscription for the open source engines – you don’t need to switch to an Enterprise version, no APIs to change, no package renames or anything. 
Just keep doing what you’re doing, but get the support and hot fixes you need for whatever size and shape production system you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://flowable.com&quot;&gt;http://flowable.com&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>You may have already seen that core developers from the Flowable Project have joined forces with edorasware. 
This doesn’t change our commitment to open source, if anything, it gives us an opportunity to do more.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 5.23.0 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/03/27/flowable-5.23.0-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 5.23.0 release" /><published>2017-03-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-03-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/03/27/flowable-5.23.0-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/03/27/flowable-5.23.0-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released a new Flowable 5.x engine version (5.23.0).
The easiest way to start using it is through the Maven:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;dependency&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;groupId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;org.flowable&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/groupId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;artifactId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;flowable-engine&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/artifactId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;5.23.0&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/dependency&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version 5 code is on the flowable5 branch on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/tree/flowable5&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/tree/flowable5&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
The version 6 code is on master &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 5.23.0 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great community contribution for collapsed sub processes by David Pardo. You now can model processes in a hierarchical way without needing to use call activities, which result in different process definitions in the Flowable Engine.
When using collapsed sub processes, the modeling part is hierarchical and using different model diagrams for the main process and the sub process models. But when deploying on the Flowable Engine, there&amp;#39;s still one process definition using embedded sub processes.
So this feature it targeted at the modeling level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bug fix for service tasks with class attributes using skip expressions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added support for using the Flowable namespace in addition to the Activiti namespace in BPMN XML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several bug fixes and smaller enhancements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible, and a special thank you to David Pardo for the Modeler contribution.
You can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions about the 5.23.0 release, any feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released a new Flowable 5.x engine version (5.23.0).
The easiest way to start using it is through the Maven:</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 6.0.0 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/02/15/flowable-6.0.0-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 6.0.0 release" /><published>2017-02-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/02/15/flowable-6.0.0-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2017/02/15/flowable-6.0.0-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released the first official Flowable 6 engine version (6.0.0). After a long period of Flowable 6 development, getting community feedback, implementing new features and bug fixes and writing documentation the version 6 is now officially out of beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6.0.0 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First official release of Flowable 6!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation has been updated to Flowable 6 and a DMN and Form Engine user guide have been added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various small bugfixes all around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Release remarks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We consider the Flowable 6 Engine stable and ready for use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We plan to release a 6.0.1 within a few weeks, so we hope to get a lot of feedback on the 6.0.0 release that we can include in a 6.0.1 release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The documentation has been extended with a DMN and Form Engine focused user guide, however the main user guide is still the BPMN user guide. We expect to do more documentation updates in the next few weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible.
You can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions about the 6.0.0 release, any feedback is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released the first official Flowable 6 engine version (6.0.0). After a long period of Flowable 6 development, getting community feedback, implementing new features and bug fixes and writing documentation the version 6 is now officially out of beta.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 6.0.0.RC1 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/12/15/flowable-6.0.0.RC1-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 6.0.0.RC1 release" /><published>2016-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/12/15/flowable-6.0.0.RC1-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/12/15/flowable-6.0.0.RC1-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released the first Flowable 6 engine version (6.0.0.RC1). This release is a major milestone before the final 6.0.0 release and we consider the version feature complete.
The focus now is to get as much feedback from the community as possible before we can release the final 6.0.0 version. Any help in this is really appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6.0.0.RC1 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package renaming to org.flowable, and renaming of config files to flowable.cfg.xml and flowable-context.xml. It was not an easy decision to go this route, but for the clear distinction and separation of the Flowable project this is the best way forward. The discussion for this choice can be found in this forum post &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org/t/opinions-on-package-renaming-for-flowable-6-to-org-flowable/118/13&quot;&gt;http://forum.flowable.org/t/opinions-on-package-renaming-for-flowable-6-to-org-flowable/118/13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class name renaming to use Flowable instead of Activiti where needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The identity functionality is separated in the IDM engine, and the identity database tables are managed by this engine. By default the IDM engine is enabled when starting the Flowable engine, but it can be disabled with the disableIdmEngine property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of a content engine, which provides a simple file store for attaching files/documents to a task or process instance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for non interrupting event sub processes. Until this version only interrupting event sub processes were supported, but now it&amp;#39;s possible to handle events and let the main process execution continue as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The task app has been refactored into 3 separate web applications. There&amp;#39;s a Flowable Modeler app that contains the modeling repository functionality + the BPMN, form and DMN editor. The second app is the Flowable IDM app that manages the users and groups and handles authentication for each app. For example the Flowable Modeler will redirect to the Flowable IDM app when no valid cookie is found. After logging in to the Flowable IDM app, a redirect to the Flowable Modeler is executed and you can access the Modeler repository. This is done to allow for single sign-on between the different apps. The third app is the Flowable task app, that allows you to start process instances and work with tasks and fill-in forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of the Flowable Admin application that allows for querying the BPM, DMN, Form and Content engines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of Docker images to make it easy to start all apps in a convenient way. In the docker folder several docker start scripts can be found that use a Docker compose file. In an upcoming blog post we will share more information on how this can be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persistency logic that was written in Hibernate has all been rewritten to MyBatis to have a common framework for all persistency logic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various and many small bugfixes all around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Release remarks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This a major milestone to get to the final Flowable 6.0.0 release. All parts of the release are now considered feature complete, so the remaining work will be bug fixing and smaller features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will continue to improve the docs for the 6.0.0 release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this point all community testing is extremely important for the quality of the 6.0.0 release. So every contribution is this area is very welcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to the whole Flowable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/team.html&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; for making this release possible.
We&amp;#39;ll do a number of blog posts in the coming days and weeks to explain the different components in the Flowable 6.0.0 RC1 package.
In the meantime you can use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; to ask specific questions and again to make the 6.0.0 release stable and well tested, please help us by testing your process definitions with this release.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released the first Flowable 6 engine version (6.0.0.RC1). This release is a major milestone before the final 6.0.0 release and we consider the version feature complete.
The focus now is to get as much feedback from the community as possible before we can release the final 6.0.0 version. Any help in this is really appreciated.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable Eclipse Designer 5.22.0 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/11/01/flowable-designer-5.22.0-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable Eclipse Designer 5.22.0 release" /><published>2016-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/11/01/flowable-designer-5.22.0-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/11/01/flowable-designer-5.22.0-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released the first Flowable Eclipse Designer version (5.22.0).
This is a fork of the Activiti Eclipse Designer with support for Eclipse Mars and Neon versions, and with a number of smaller fixes and features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code can be found on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-designer&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-designer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The update site can be found of &lt;a href=&quot;http://flowable.org/designer/update&quot;&gt;http://flowable.org/designer/update&lt;/a&gt;.
The zip file of the update site can also be downloaded from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flowable.org/designer/archived/flowable-designer-5.22.0.zip&quot;&gt;http://www.flowable.org/designer/archived/flowable-designer-5.22.0.zip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please let us know if you encounter bugs or if you are looking for specific features on the forum &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;http://forum.flowable.org&lt;/a&gt;,
and by creating issues on the Github issues page &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-designer/issues&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-designer/issues&lt;/a&gt;.
The developers of the Flowable project are keen to help you answering your questions and helping out with possible issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released the first Flowable Eclipse Designer version (5.22.0).
This is a fork of the Activiti Eclipse Designer with support for Eclipse Mars and Neon versions, and with a number of smaller fixes and features.</summary></entry><entry><title>Flowable 5.22.0 release</title><link href="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/10/13/flowable-5.22.0-release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flowable 5.22.0 release" /><published>2016-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/10/13/flowable-5.22.0-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.flowable.org/blog/2016/10/13/flowable-5.22.0-release.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we released the first Flowable engine version (5.22.0). This release is a fork of  Activiti 5.21.0. There have been no package renaming or config file name changes.
The easiest way to start using it is through the Maven:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;dependency&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;groupId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;org.flowable&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/groupId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;artifactId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;flowable-engine&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/artifactId&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;5.22.0&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/dependency&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version 5 code is on the flowable5 branch on Github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/tree/flowable5&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/tree/flowable5&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
The version 6 code is on master &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 5.22.0 release has the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First Flowable release. With a new Maven group (org.flowable) and artefact id (flowable-engine etc), there are no changes to package names or config file names in the fork of Activiti.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of transient variables. Transient variables won&amp;#39;t be persisted in the process variable tables, but are still available on the execution for the duration of a single transaction. 
Transient variables can for example be used to store a REST response that is only needed to create a request to another REST service, or to use a Java service task result in the next 
Java service task without it getting persisted. You can read more about it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jorambarrez.be/blog/2016/09/01/how-to-use-transient-variables-in-activiti/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several bug fixes and smaller enhancements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people will also be wondering what will happen with the version 6 engine. It&amp;#39;s our main focus to get a new beta release out as soon as possible and 
we want to get the final 6.0 release out shortly after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand that there will be a bit of confusion around starting the Flowable project. We don&amp;#39;t plan any package renaming or config filename changes for example. For now, please get in contact with us through the forum &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.flowable.org&quot;&gt;http://forum.flowable.org&lt;/a&gt;,
and by creating issues on the Github issues page &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/issues&quot;&gt;https://github.com/flowable/flowable-engine/issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
The developers of the Flowable project are keen to help you answering your questions and helping out with possible issues.&lt;br&gt;
The 5.22.0 release is the starting point for the Flowable project, a lot more releases will follow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>flowable</name></author><summary>Today we released the first Flowable engine version (5.22.0). This release is a fork of  Activiti 5.21.0. There have been no package renaming or config file name changes.
The easiest way to start using it is through the Maven:</summary></entry></feed>
